A Guide to the Correspondence and Subject Files of the Executive Director of the Virginia Indigent Defense Commission, 1972-2003
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the Correspondence and Subject Files of the Executive Director of the Virginia Indigent Defense Commission, 1972-2003
The Library of Virginia
42602
28 cubic foot (28 boxes)
Virginia Indigent Defense Commission
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by the Virginia Indigent Defense Commission, March 24, 2006.
Biographical Information
The Virginia Public Defender Commission was created on 10 April 1972 according to Chapter 2.1 of the Acts of Assembly. In 1972, the Commission consisted of five members appointed by the Speaker of the House of Delegates in consultation with the Chairman of the Courts of Justice Committees of the Senate and House of Delegates. Following a successful pilot project, three offices were authorized in Augusta County, Virginia Beach, and the City of Roanoke in 1976. Offices were later added throughout the Commonwealth. The Commission establishes standards for the qualification of counsel appointed in capital cases and maintains lists of counsel for use by the circuit courts.
In 2004, the General Assembly created the Virginia Indigent Defense Commission to replace the Virginia Public Defender Commission. The mission of the Virginia Indigent Defense Commission is to enhance the quality of justice throughout Virginia by protecting the rights of the criminally accused through high quality, compassionate, and cost-effective legal representation. The Commission is responsible for providing oversight and support for all attorneys who furnish indigent defense service in the Commonwealth. The Commission consists of twelve members including the chairmen of the House and Senate Committees for Courts of Justice, the chairman of the Virginia State Crime Commission, the Executive Secretary of the Supreme Court, two attorneys officially designated by the Virginia State Bar, two persons appointed by the Governor, two persons appointed by the Speaker of the House of Delegates, and two persons appointed by the Senate Committee on Rules.
Scope and Content
Correspondence and subject files of the Executive Director of the Virginia Indigent Defense Commission, 1972-2003, document the planning, direction, and implementation of Commission programs and are evidence of actions and policy decisions. Contains memos, correspondence, financial records, complaints, minutes, annual reports, newsletters, and other sundry items belonging to the Executive Director of the Virginia Indigent Defense Commission. The director maintained various files related to public defender offices, studies, budget, commission meetings, etc.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged in original order.
Contents List
- Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-2003.
  - Motor Vehicles - State owned, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Moving, Relocation Policy, 2000. (Box 1)
  - Rule 3A:15.1 - Newly Discovered Evidence, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Newsletter - The Virginia Defender, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - National Center for State Courts, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Newport News, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - No Parole legislation, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Office lease procedures, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Sprinklers, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Overhead allowance, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Parking regulations, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Part-time employees - Memo re: nonpayment of accumulated sick leave, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Parole and Probation Compact - Administrators Association Manual, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Pay schedules, 1994. (Box 1)
  - PD - Successful appeals, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Pinkerton - Miscellaneous, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Prince William County Bar Association - Interest in Capital Defense Seminar (NOVA), 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Posting minutes online, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Public Defenders - Meeting preferences, 2002 June. (Box 1)
  - Proposed Office - Bristol, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Proposed Office - Brunswick, Greensville, Surry, Sussex and Emporia, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Pre-Office - Chesterfield, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Public Defender Office - Greensville / Brunswick Counties, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Pre-Office - Loudoun, Fauquier, Rappahannock, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Public Defender / Court Appointed Committee, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Pre-Office - Pittsylvania, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Pre-Office - Rockbridge / Buena Vista, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Pre-Office - Salem / Roanoke, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Pre-Office - Bristol / Smyth / Washington, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Pre-Office - Williamsburg / York, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Pre-Office - Richmond Office relocation, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Press releases, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Procurement Policies, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Reappropriation request - Unexpended sum, 1989. (Box 1)
  - Resolution - Ann Frederick Downes, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Applicants / Interviews for possible positions, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Request for Commission Report, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Long distance calls, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Judge Robertson correspondence, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Risk Management, 1972-2003. (Box 1)
  - Salaries / Public Defender Retreat, 2000. (Box 1)
  - Public Defender Salaries - Editorials, Correspondence, 1972-2003. (Box 2)
  - Pay increases, 1972-2003. (Box 2)
  - Salary information, 1972-2003. (Box 2)
  - Salary sheets, 1972-2003. (Box 2)
  - Report of the Secretary of Administration, 1972-2003. (Box 2)
  - Schley resignation, 1972-2003. (Box 2)
  - Tuition / Payment, 1972-2003. (Box 2)
  - Virginia Public Defender Program Summary of Public Defender Legislation, 1972-2003. (Box 2)
  - Virginia Acts of Assembly, 1972-2003. (Box 2)
  - Youthful Offender Program, 1972-2003. (Box 2)
  - Career Defender Committee, 1972-2003. (Box 2)
  - Salaries - Career Defenders, 1972-2003. (Box 2)